{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following States is Dampa Tiger Reserve situated?",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionD": "  Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDampha Tiger Reserve is the largest wildlife sanctuary of Mizoram. It is situated on the border of India with Banglades in western mizoram.",
            "keyString": "88343s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following region in India is now regarded as an \"Ecological Hot Spot\"?",
            "optionA": "  Western Himalayas ",
            "optionB": "  Eastern Himalayas ",
            "optionC": "  Western Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWestern Ghats have around 1800 endemic species. Most of them are endangered due to human activities in the region. Hence, it is made the bio-diversity hot spot so as to save receding species of this region.",
            "keyString": "88378s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Manas Sanctuary in Assam is known for",
            "optionA": "  Elephants ",
            "optionB": "  Bears ",
            "optionC": "  Tigers ",
            "optionD": "  Wild ass ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tManas Sanctuary is famous for elephants. It is situated in Assam. It is also famous for Project Tiger. ",
            "keyString": "88394s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Bio-Reserves in India is the natural habitat for lions?",
            "optionA": "  Nilgiri Bio-Reserve ",
            "optionB": "  Kaziranga Bio-Reserve ",
            "optionC": "  Mudumalai Bio-Reserve ",
            "optionD": "  Gir Bio-Reserve ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Gir forests are natural habitat of Asiatic lions. Its known as Gir Forest National Park & Wildlife Santuary. It is located in Kathiawar region of Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "88407s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the first scheme of \"Biosphere Reserve Areas\"?",
            "optionA": "  Sundarban Biosphere Reserve ",
            "optionB": "  Nilgiri Biosphere Reserve ",
            "optionC": "  Nanda Devi Biosphere Reserve ",
            "optionD": "  Gulf of Mannar Biosphere Reserve ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiosphere Reserve Areas are the regions established by Indian government as 'Biosphere Reserve' in accordance with IUCN Category-V Protected areas. These are larger areas of natural habitat including one or more National Parks accompanied by buffer zones. Nilgiri Biosphere Reserve was first of this kind. ",
            "keyString": "88419s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionB": "  Orissa ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBharatpur bird sanctuary is located in Rajasthan state & bordering with the state of Uttar Pradesh. Also known as Koeladeo Ghana Bird Sanctuary or Koeladeo National Park. Being a World Heritage Site it is famous for migratory Siberian Cranes. ",
            "keyString": "173109s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Manas Wildlife Sanctuary is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionD": "  Chattisgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tManas Wildlife Sanctuary is located in Assam, It is also a National Park and UNESCO World Heritage Site, Project Tiger & Elephant reserve. ",
            "keyString": "173147s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India's Biosphere Reserve 'Nanda Devi' (UNESCO) is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "optionB": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionC": "   Meghalaya ",
            "optionD": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNanda Devi Biosphere Reserve comprises of Nanda Devi & Valley of Flowers National Park. It is drained by Rishi Ganga river.",
            "keyString": "173164s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The study of relation of animals and plants to their surroundings is called as",
            "optionA": "  Ecology ",
            "optionB": "  Ethrology ",
            "optionC": "  Genealogy ",
            "optionD": "  Iconology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is Greek word made up of two words \"Eco\" & \"Logy\". 'Eco' means 'environment' & 'logy' means 'study'. Ecology term was coined by Ernst Heckel. It studies the interaction of living beings with their environment.",
            "keyString": "173180s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is a famous bird sanctuary located in Haryana?",
            "optionA": "  Sultanpur ",
            "optionB": "  Bharatpur ",
            "optionC": "  Rajaji ",
            "optionD": "  Sariska ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSultanpur Bird Sanctuary lies between Gurugram and Delhi in the Northern state of Haryana. It is named after Rajput king Sultan Chauhan. ",
            "keyString": "173193s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Forest Reserch Insititute located?",
            "optionA": "  Dehradun ",
            "optionB": "  Bhopal ",
            "optionC": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tForest Research Institute is located in Dehradun, Uttarakhand. It is operated by Indian Council of Forestry Research and Education. ",
            "keyString": "250831s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "First national park of India that was established in 1936 was named as",
            "optionA": "  Kanha National Park ",
            "optionB": "  Bharatpur National Park ",
            "optionC": "  Hailey National Park ",
            "optionD": "  Rajaji National Park ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHailey National Park which is also called as Jim Corbett National Park is in Nainital in Uttarakhand. It was established in 1936. It has tigers, elephants & Hundreds of bird species. ",
            "keyString": "250867s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Afforestation is the process of",
            "optionA": "  Cleaning forests ",
            "optionB": "  Plantation ",
            "optionC": "  Cutting of forest ",
            "optionD": "  Collecting forest resources ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfforestation is the planting of trees in the area where there was no forest cover earlier. It can also be termed as establishment of forests.",
            "keyString": "250884s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kanha National Park saving the rare and almost extinct species of the Swamp Deer, also known as",
            "optionA": "  Barasingha ",
            "optionB": "  Black Buck ",
            "optionC": "  Chinkara ",
            "optionD": "  Nilgai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSwamp deer is a deer species distributed in the Indian subcontinent. Kanha National Park in Madhya Pradesh is a home for this specie. Swamp deer is also known as \"Barasingha\". ",
            "keyString": "250897s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the first national park of India?",
            "optionA": "  Jim Corbett National Park ",
            "optionB": "  Similipal National Park ",
            "optionC": "  Dachigam National Park ",
            "optionD": "  Hazaribagh National Park ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEarlier known as Hailey National Park, Jim Corbett National Park got established in 1936. in Nainital to Protect Bengal tiger. ",
            "keyString": "250910s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Symbiotic Bacteria responsible for the fixation of atmospheric nitrogen are present in",
            "optionA": "  Peas ",
            "optionB": "  Wheat ",
            "optionC": "  Corn ",
            "optionD": "  Oats ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSymbiotic bacteria responsible for the fixation of atmospheric nitrogen are present in peas. The symbiotic nitrogen-fixing bacteria invade the root hairs of host plants, where they multiply and stimulate formation of root nodules, enlargements of plant cells and bacteria in intimate association.",
            "keyString": "315492s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kugti Wildlife Sanctuary is located in which of the following state",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Jammu & Kasmir ",
            "optionC": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Chamba city of Himachal Pradesh Kugti Wildlife Sanctuary is located at altitude of about 2195m to 5040m.It is the largest sanctuary of Himachal Pradesh, It has snow leopard, musk marten brown langur etc.",
            "keyString": "315532s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dandeli Wildlife Sanctuary is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Orissa ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDandeli Wildlife Sanctuary is located in Karnataka. Under the project tiger Anshi National Park and Dandeli Wildlife Sanctuary were collectively declared as Dandeli National Park. ",
            "keyString": "315554s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chipko Andolan is related to whom?",
            "optionA": "  Wild Life Conservation ",
            "optionB": "  Conservation of Forests ",
            "optionC": "  Agro-Science ",
            "optionD": "  Deforestation ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChipko Andolan is also termed as Chipko Movement. It was a forest conservation movement in Garhwal Himalayas which started in 1973. ",
            "keyString": "315569s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The objective of Biosphere Reserve is",
            "optionA": "  Preservation of flora and fauna of forest land ",
            "optionB": "  Research and Development of forest product ",
            "optionC": "  Research and Development of agro product ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the above given options are correct in terms of objective of biosphere reserve. hence (D) is right option. The objective of Biosphere Reserves are Preservation of flora and fauna of forest land, Research and Development of forest product and Research and Development of agro product. ",
            "keyString": "315582s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mudumalai wildlife sanctuary is famous for",
            "optionA": "  Tiger ",
            "optionB": "  Bison ",
            "optionC": "  Birds ",
            "optionD": "  Elephants ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMudumalai Wildlife Sanctuary is famous for its tiger reserve, it lies in North-west of Nilgiri Hills(Blue Mountains), Tamil Nadu sharing its boundaries with Kerala & Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "403354s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Silent valley of Kerala",
            "optionA": "  Is only Evergreen Forest in India ",
            "optionB": "  Has trees of expensive construction wood ",
            "optionC": "   Is famous for picnic spot ",
            "optionD": "  Has rare species of Flora and Fauna. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilent Valley has tropical rain forests and temperate forests in higher reaches which are rare in this region. Most plant species are endemic to Western Ghats. Similarly, NilgiriTahr, Nilgiri Langur, liun tailed macaque are all endangered fauna species which are rare to be found. ",
            "keyString": "403877s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following weeds is effective in controlling water pollution caused by industrial effluents?",
            "optionA": "  Parthenium ",
            "optionB": "  Elephant grass ",
            "optionC": "  Water hyacinth ",
            "optionD": "  Mogar grass ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWater hyacinth (Eichhornia crassipes) is used for purifying not only domestic wastewater but also industrial wastewater. It can readily absorb, accumulate and concentrate heavy metals such as lead, cadmium, mercury and nickel. Other studies have evaluated the potential of water hyacinth to absorb various organic chemicals like phenols and toxaphene. Water hyacinth can remove even radioactive metals from industrial effluents, which is very difficult otherwise.",
            "keyString": "404390s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The state which produces largest number of orchids in India is",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionD": "  Sikkim ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLargest number of orchids are produced by Sikkim in India, Arunachal Pradesh has the capability to surpass Sikkim in this aspect. ",
            "keyString": "404945s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Total number of biosphere reserves in India are",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  15 ",
            "optionD": "  18 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are 18 biosphere reserves in India, of these only 4 are UNESCO acclaimed International Biosphere Reserves, These are Nanda Devi, Sundarban, Nilgiri & Gulf of Mannar Biosphere Reserves.",
            "keyString": "405392s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Kanha National Park?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanha National Park is in Madhya Pradesh. Also known as Tiger Reserve,it has wild pigs, jackals and tigers. ",
            "keyString": "488327s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state in India has the largest cover area of forest?",
            "optionA": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadhya Pradesh with a forest cover of about 77,462 square kilometers ranks first in the list of forest cover. It is followed by Arunachal Pradesh with a forest cover of about 67,248 sq. km.",
            "keyString": "488362s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state has the highest percentage of forest?",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionC": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWith 90% (approx) Mizoram has highest percentage of forest as per availble options. ",
            "keyString": "488379s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kanha National Park belongs to which one among the following biogeographical areas in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Tropical Sub-humid Forests ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical Humid Forests ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical Dry Forests ",
            "optionD": "  Tropical Moist Forests ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanha National Park belongs to tropical sub-humid Forests one among the following biogeographical areas in the world. Kanha National Park, also known as Kanha Tiger Reserve, is a vast expanse of grassland and forest in the central Indian state of Madhya Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "488394s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bandipur National Park is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBandipur National Park is situated in Cliamara janagar district of Karnataka. This National Park is famous for its small population of tigers.",
            "keyString": "488407s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "This is the only sanctuary where Kashmiri Deer are found?",
            "optionA": "  Kanha ",
            "optionB": "  Dachigam ",
            "optionC": "  Gir ",
            "optionD": "  Mudumalai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDachigam is a well known habitat for the Hangul (Kashmir Stag). They can be easily spotted in winters, when they hang out in the lower valleys. Other inhabitants at Dachigam are Musk deer, Brown Bear, Leopards, Jungle Cats, Himalayan black bear, and a few species of wild goat like the markhor and ibex. ",
            "keyString": "571656s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The only sanctuary where kasturi stag is found is",
            "optionA": "  Kanha ",
            "optionB": "  Dachigam ",
            "optionC": "  Gir ",
            "optionD": "   Mudumalai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDachigam National Park located 22 km north of Srinagar in J & K has musk deer (Kasturi Mrig). Dachigam is made up of 10 Villages (Das Gaam).",
            "keyString": "571707s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Asiatic black bear and snow leopard is found in which of the following places?",
            "optionA": "  Sundarbans National Park ",
            "optionB": "  Nanda Devi and Valley of Flowers National Parks ",
            "optionC": "  Keoladeo National Park ",
            "optionD": "  Manas Wildlife Sanctuary ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNanda Devi and Valley of Flowers both National Parks are located in Uttarakhand state of India. Apartfrom a wide variety of flora these include fauna like Snow leopard & Asiatic black bear.",
            "keyString": "571863s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Heri Tiera Fomes (sundari tree) is a type of which of the following plants?",
            "optionA": "  Tidal Forest ",
            "optionB": "  Thorn Forest ",
            "optionC": "  Mountain Forest ",
            "optionD": "  Taiga Forest ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHeritiera Fomes (Sundari tree) is a type of mangrove tree mostly found in the Sundarban delta of Ganga Brahmaputra rivers. It constitutes over 70% of forest in this area. ",
            "keyString": "571997s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements on biosphere reserves is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  In 1973, UNESCO launched a worldwide programme on man and biosphere ",
            "optionB": "  Biosphere reserves promote research on ecological conservation ",
            "optionC": "  Nanda Devi Biosphere Reserve is located in Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Biosphere reserves are multipurpose protected areas to preserve the genetic diversity in ecosystems ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nanda Devi National Park or Nanda Devi Biosphere Reserve, established in 1982 , is a national park situated around the peak of Nanda Devi (7816 m) in the state of Uttarakhand in northern India. ",
            "keyString": "572130s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Gir Forest is noted for its",
            "optionA": "  Lion Sanctuary ",
            "optionB": "  Deer park ",
            "optionC": "  Tiger sanctuary ",
            "optionD": "  Crocodile Park ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGir Forest is located in Kathiarwar Peninsular region. These are famous for Asiatic lions. It lies in state of Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "640031s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivpuri National Park of Madhya Pradesh is famous for which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Tiger and elephant ",
            "optionB": "  Wild Bison ",
            "optionC": "  Birds ",
            "optionD": "  Leopard and Spotted deer ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShivpuri National Park of M.P. is also known as Madhav National Park named after Madhav Rao Scindia, Raja of Gwalior. Set up in 1958, it is composed of dry decidous& flat grasslands. ",
            "keyString": "640066s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state has, the highest percentage of forest cover?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Manipur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDue to moist & humid climatic conditions towards the North-East India, almost all states are rich flora & fauna. ",
            "keyString": "640082s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following types of forests exhibits highest bio-diversity ?",
            "optionA": "  Dry deciduous forest ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical rain forest ",
            "optionC": "  Moist deciduous forest ",
            "optionD": "  Mangrove forest ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTropical rain forest types of forests exhibits highest bio-diversity. Tropical rainforests are known for their extreme biodiversity, posing a challenging problem in tropical ecology. A rain forest is simply an area of tall, mostly evergreen trees and a high amount of rainfall. ",
            "keyString": "640095s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bandhavgarh National Park is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Jharkhand ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBandhavgarah National Park is one of the popular National Parks in India located in the Umaria district of Madhya Pradesh. The density of the tiger population at Bandhavgarh is one of the highest known in India. It has a large breeding population of leopards and various species of deer. ",
            "keyString": "640108s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are considered a Renewable Source of Energy?\n1. Wind Energy\n2. Solar Energy\n3. Nuclear Energy",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 3 ",
            "optionD": "  Only 1 and 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWind Energy and Solar Energy is considered a Renewable Source of Energy. Renewable energy is any energy that comes from natural resources such as wind, water, sunlight and geothermal heat, which is heat that is retained in the earth. ",
            "keyString": "761246s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kalakkad-Mundanthurai Tiger Reserve is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionC": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeclared as 17th tiger reserve of India, Kalkad Mundathurai tiger reserve (KMTR) is the 2nd largest reserve area of Tamil Nadu. It was established in 1988. ",
            "keyString": "761359s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements\nI. Jim Corbett National Park is the oldest National Park of India.\nII. It was one of the nine Tiger Reserves created at the launch of the Project Tiger in 1973.\nIII. Initially it was named as 'Haile National Park'.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  I and III ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the given statements are correct. Jim Corbett National Park is the oldest National Park of India. It was one of the nine Tiger Reserves created at the launch of the Project Tiger in 1973. Initially it was named as 'Haile National Park'. ",
            "keyString": "761377s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Melghat Tiger Reserve is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "   Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "   Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMelghat tiger reserve which is located in the Amravatidistrict of Maharashtra was among the nine tiger reserves which were declared under the first phase of project tiger in 1973-74. ",
            "keyString": "761402s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indravati Tiger Reserve is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Telangana ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionD": "  West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndravati Tiger Reserve is located in Dantewada district of Chattisgarh. This National Park is the best potential habitat for the wild buffalo.",
            "keyString": "761430s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Great Himalayan National Park is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Sikkim ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGreat Himalayan national Park is located in Kullu region of Himachal Pradesh. It is a UNESCO world Heritage site conserving some globally threatened species such as deer and western Horned tragopan. ",
            "keyString": "866184s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What will be the effect of global warming on Mangrove forests?",
            "optionA": "  They will growin large number ",
            "optionB": "  Big area of mangrove forest will be submerged ",
            "optionC": "  Their role as carbon sinks will become more important ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs the mangroves act as buffer between sea & land being found in coastal regions they are considered most vulnerable to rising sea water level. ",
            "keyString": "866251s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state is the Kanger Ghati National Park?",
            "optionA": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "   Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Chhatisgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanger Ghati National Park is situated in Jagdalpur, Chhatisgarh in Bastar region. It became a National Park in 1982. It has Bastar hill myna as one the prominent species. ",
            "keyString": "866267s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has been declared as the marine park by Indian government for the conservation of Coral Reef?",
            "optionA": "  Gulf of Kutch ",
            "optionB": "  Lakshadweep Island ",
            "optionC": "  Andaman Islands ",
            "optionD": "  Gulf of Mannar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGulf of Kutch is located near Gujarat state of India. It has fringing reefs which are a bit less developed due to high sea temperatures & high salinity. It has been declared as the Marine Park by Indian goverment for conservation of corals. ",
            "keyString": "866281s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following has the maximum number of National Parks?",
            "optionA": "  Andaman and Nicobar Islands ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAndaman and Nicobar Islands has the maximum number of National Parks. Total number of National Parks in Andaman and Nicobar Islands is Nine (9). ",
            "keyString": "866294s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the non-conventional sources of energy in India?",
            "optionA": "  Solar Energy ",
            "optionB": "  Geo-Thermal Energy ",
            "optionC": "  Thermal Energy ",
            "optionD": "  Tidal Power ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThermal Energy is not one of the non-conventional sources of energy in India. Thermal energy is the energy that comes from heat. This heat is generated by the movement of tiny particles within an object. The faster these particles move, the more heat is generated. ",
            "keyString": "958886s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Biodiversity hotspots are located only in tropical regions.\n2. India has four biodiversity hotspots, i.e., Eastern Himalayas, Western Himalayas, Western Ghats and Andaman and Nicobar Islands.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth the statements are incorrect. Currently, 35 biodiversity hotspots have been identified, most of which occur in tropical forests. They represent just 2.3% of Earth's land surface, but between them they contain around 50% of the world's endemic plant species and 42% of all terrestrial vertebrates. India hosts 4 biodiversity hotspots:the Himalayas, the Western Ghats, the Indo-Burma region and the Sundaland (Includes Nicobar group of Islands). ",
            "keyString": "958918s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is a global biodiversity hotspot in India?",
            "optionA": "  Western Ghats ",
            "optionB": "  Western Himalayas ",
            "optionC": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  Northern Himalayas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia has some of the world's most biodiverse regions. It hosts 4 biodiversity hotspots : the Himalayas, the Western Ghats, the Indo-Burma region and the Sundaland (Includes Nicobar group of Islands). These hotspots have numerous endemic species. ",
            "keyString": "958934s2m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In terms of area, which of the following Indian state has the largest forest cover?",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Chattisgarh ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn terms of area, Madhya Pradesh has the largest forest cover. Madhya Pradesh with more than 77,000 sq kms of area forest cover. ",
            "keyString": "13208s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kanchenjunga National Park is located in",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKanchenjunga National Park, also known as Khangchendzonga National Park, located in Sikkim. It is also a biosphere reserve. It became the World Heritage Site on 17 July 2016. It has musk deers, snow leopard as an important species. ",
            "keyString": "13272s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The boundaries of a National Park are defined by legislation.\n2. A Biosphere Reserve is declared to conserve a few specific species of flora and fauna.\n3. In a Wildlife Sanctuary, limited biotic interference is permitted.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statements given that are correct are the boundaries of a National Park are defined by legislation and in a Wildlife Sanctuary, limited biotic interference is permitted. ",
            "keyString": "13293s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most dangerous effect of excessive deforestation is",
            "optionA": "  Loss of forest ",
            "optionB": "  Loss of other plants ",
            "optionC": "  Destruction of habitat of wild animals ",
            "optionD": "  Soil erosion ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDestruction of habitat of wild animals, As the forests are shrinking due to deforestation, the wild animals are loosing on their natural habitits risking survival.",
            "keyString": "13319s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two important rivers - one with its source in Jharkhand (and known by a different name in Odisha), and another, with its source in Odisha - merge at a place only a short distance from the coast of Bay of Bengal before flowing into the sea. This is an important site of wildlife and biodiversity and a protected area. Which one of the following could be this?",
            "optionA": "  Bhitarkanika ",
            "optionB": "  Chandipur-on-sea ",
            "optionC": "  Gopalpur-on-sea ",
            "optionD": "  Simlipal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhitarkanika is a unique habitat of Mangrove Forests criss-crossed with numerous creeks and mud flats located in Kendrapara district of Orissa. One of the largest Mangrove Eco systems in India, Bhitarkanika is home to diverse flora and fauna. ",
            "keyString": "13336s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The natural habitat of Rhinoceros in India is",
            "optionA": "  Bharatpur ",
            "optionB": "  Gir forest ",
            "optionC": "   Kaziranga ",
            "optionD": "  Nilgiris ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhaziranga National Park with 2/3 rd of one horned rhinoceros of the world is the natural habitat of rhinoceros in India. ",
            "keyString": "124198s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Red Data Book provides an account of",
            "optionA": "  Extinct animals only ",
            "optionB": "  Endangered plants & animals ",
            "optionC": "  Endangered plants only ",
            "optionD": "  Fossil plants ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRed Data Book released by International Union for Conservation of Nature is regarding endangered & vulnerable biotic species (plants and animals). It was started in 1964. ",
            "keyString": "124236s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following wild life sanctuary of India, where project of conservation of Rhinos is underway?",
            "optionA": "  Bandipur ",
            "optionB": "  Periyar ",
            "optionC": "  Kaziranga ",
            "optionD": "  Gir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaziranga National Park has about 2/3 rd of world's great one horned rhinoceroses. It is situated in Assam as a renowned \"World Heritage Site\". ",
            "keyString": "124256s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Main constituents of biogas are",
            "optionA": "  Methane and carbon monoxide ",
            "optionB": "  Butane and carbon monoxide ",
            "optionC": "  Methane and carbon dioxide ",
            "optionD": "  Ethylene and carbon dioxide ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMain constituents of biogas are Methane and carbon dioxide. Biogas comprises primarily methane (CH4) and carbon dioxide (CO2) and may have small amounts of hydrogen sulphide (H2S), moisture and siloxanes. ",
            "keyString": "124272s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest Biosphere Reserve of India?",
            "optionA": "  Nilgiri ",
            "optionB": "  Nanda Devi ",
            "optionC": "  Sundarban ",
            "optionD": "  Gulf of mannar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis Biosphere Reserve is also known as Gulf of Mannar Marine National Park. It is largest of biosphere reserves in India. It is located between India & Sri Lanka in Indian Ocean as shallow water body. A rare species dugong (Sea cow) is found here. ",
            "keyString": "124304s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Nagarhole National Park?",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Orissa ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagarhole National Park is also called Rajiv Gandhi National Park. It is situated in Kogadu and Mysore districts of Kamataka. It is part of the Nilgiri Biosphere Reserve. It has many tigers, Indian bison and elephants. ",
            "keyString": "177767s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The state which has attained the dubious distinction of being topper in the list with the highest encroachment of forest land ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Haryana ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe state Haryana has attained the dubious distinction of being a topper in the list with the highest encroachment of forest land. ",
            "keyString": "177803s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How much geographical area of India is forest land?",
            "optionA": "  20% ",
            "optionB": "  23% ",
            "optionC": "  26% ",
            "optionD": "  28% ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia has 20% of its land under forest. In recent times forest area has depleted. ",
            "keyString": "177820s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which kind of forest is found in Silent Valley of Kerala?",
            "optionA": "  Mangrove Forest ",
            "optionB": "  Deciduous Forest ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical Rain Forest ",
            "optionD": "  Littoral and Swamp Forest ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilent valley is a National Park in Nilgiri Hills in Kerala's Palakkad District. It consists of tropical rainforests & moist deciduous forests. Along with Karimpuzha & Mukurthi National Park, it forms the part of Nilgiri International Biosphere Reserve. ",
            "keyString": "177833s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Corbett National Park was established to protect which animal?",
            "optionA": "  Bengal Tigers ",
            "optionB": "  Snow Leopards ",
            "optionC": "  Asiatic Lions ",
            "optionD": "  One Horned Rhinos ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo protect the endangered Bengal Tiger, Jim Corbett National Park was established in 1936 in the Nainital district of Uttrakhand. It is the oldest National Park of India.",
            "keyString": "177845s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Silent valley is located in",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Africa ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilent valley is a National Park in Nilgiri Hills in Kerala's Palakkad District. It consists of tropical rainforests & moist deciduous forests. Alongwith Karimpuzha & Mukurthi National Park, it forms the part of Nilgiri International Biosphere Reserve.",
            "keyString": "248996s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following non-conventional sources of energy holds out the maximum promise in India?",
            "optionA": "  Solar Energy ",
            "optionB": "  Geothermal Energy ",
            "optionC": "  Tidal Energy ",
            "optionD": "  Wind Energy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSolar Energy non-conventional sources of energy holds out the maximum promise in India. Solar energy is harnessed by converting solar energy directly into electrical energy in solar plants. Photosynthesis process carries out this process of conversion of solar energy. In photosynthesis, green plants absorb solar energy and convert it into chemical energy. Solar energy is an essential energy of all non-conventional sources but its usage amount is very less. It is the most important non-conventional source of energy and it gives non-polluting environment-friendly output and is available in abundant. ",
            "keyString": "249197s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is meant by 'energy crisis'?",
            "optionA": "  Shortage of hydro-electricity ",
            "optionB": "  Malnutrition leading to short supply of energy in the human body ",
            "optionC": "  Shortage of the thermal power ",
            "optionD": "  Impending danger of total exhaustion of fossil fuels like coal and petroleum ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn energy crisis is any significant bottleneck in the supply of energy resources to an economy. It often refers to one of the energy sources used at a certain time and place, in particular those that supply national electricity grids or those used as fuel in vehicles. ",
            "keyString": "249376s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "World's only floating National Park is located in",
            "optionA": "  Manipur ",
            "optionB": "  Kuala Lumpur ",
            "optionC": "  Bilaspur ",
            "optionD": "  Dispur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKeibul Lamjao National Park is situated on Lake Loktak in Bishnupur district of Manipur state in NE India and is the only floating park in the world. ",
            "keyString": "249549s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a site for 'in-situ' method of conservation of flora?",
            "optionA": "  Biosphere Reserve ",
            "optionB": "  Botanical Garden ",
            "optionC": "  National Park ",
            "optionD": "  Wildlife Sanctuary ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBotanical Garden is not a site for 'in-situ' method of conservation of flora. In-situ conservation is on site conservation or the conservation of genetic resources in natural populations of plant or animal species, such as forest genetic resources in natural populations of tree species. ",
            "keyString": "249717s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Simlipal Tiger Reserve is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSimlipal tiger reserve (also a National Park) is situated in Mayurbhaj district of Odisha. This tiger reserve derived its name 'Similipal' form 'Simul' tree i.e. Silk Cotton tree. ",
            "keyString": "314351s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Anamalai Tiger Reserve is in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Telangana ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnamalai Tiger reserve is a 950 sq. km. reserve spread over Western Ghats in Tamil Nadu. It was declared a tiger reserve in 2007. ",
            "keyString": "314585s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find the wrong pair",
            "optionA": "  Bandipur National Park - Karnataka ",
            "optionB": "  Sariska National Park - Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Annamalai National Park - Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Periyar National Park - Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPeriyar National Park is in Kerala in Western Ghats. It is also called Periyar Tiger Reserve, Apart tigers it has lion tailed macaques, leopards, Indian bison etc, To its North, it has 'Periyar lake'.",
            "keyString": "314785s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the Organisation is mainly related with environmental planning?",
            "optionA": "  CSIR ",
            "optionB": "  NEERI ",
            "optionC": "  CIFRI ",
            "optionD": "  ICAR ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNEERI stands for National Environmental Engineering Research Institute which is run by Government of India. It is situated in Nagpur and was established in 1958. It has 5 laboratories at Kolkata, Hyderabad, Delhi, Chennai, Mumbai. ",
            "keyString": "314975s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which sanctuary in India is famous for Rhinoceros and in which state is it located?",
            "optionA": "  Gir, Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Kaziranga, Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Ranthambore, Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Corbett, Uttarakhand ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaziranga National Park (pronounced Assamese pronunciation) is a national park in the Golaghat and Nagaon districts of the state of Assam, India. The sanctuary, which hosts two-thirds of the world's great one-horned rhinoceroses, is a World Heritage Site. ",
            "keyString": "315159s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Panchmari Biosphere Reserve located?",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPanchmari Biosphere Reserve is located in midst of Satpura Ranges in Madhya Pradesh. It was designated as biosphere reserve in 2009 by UNESCO. It act as transition zone between forest species of western & eastern ghats. e.g. wild boar gaur, cheetal deer. ",
            "keyString": "380030s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sea-cow is found in which of the following biosphere\nreserve of India",
            "optionA": "  Nokrek ",
            "optionB": "  Gulf of Mannar ",
            "optionC": "  Manas ",
            "optionD": "  Sundarban ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGulf of Mannar is situated between Coromandal Coast of India & Sri Lanka. It is a shallow water zone. It has many endangered species which are native to this region. One such specie is dugong dugong, a herbivorous marine mammal. ",
            "keyString": "380329s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a new bio-fertilizers?",
            "optionA": "  Green Blue Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Nitrates ",
            "optionC": "  Compost ",
            "optionD": "  Farmyard manure ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGreen Blue Algae is a new bio-fertilizers. Cyanobacteria, or blue-green algae, is one such example of a bio-fertilizer, a type of organic fertilizer which contains living organisms and harnesses naturally occurring inputs like solar energy, nitrogen, and water to ensure soil fertility and plant growth. ",
            "keyString": "380539s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following resource is abiotic and renewable?",
            "optionA": "  Iron Ore ",
            "optionB": "  Livestock ",
            "optionC": "  Water ",
            "optionD": "  Forest ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWater is abiotic i.e. non-living & renewable that is recyclable & reusable.",
            "keyString": "380742s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Malaghat Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Kanha Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Manas Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Periyar Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPeriyar National Park is in Kerala in Western Ghats. It is also called Periyar Tiger Reserve, Apart tigers it has lion tailed macaques, leopards, Indian bison etc, To its North, it has 'Periyar lake'.",
            "keyString": "380916s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Keoladeo Ghana National Park in Rajasthan was formerly called as",
            "optionA": "  Salim AliBird Sanctuary ",
            "optionB": "  Khijadia Bird Sanctuary ",
            "optionC": "   Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary ",
            "optionD": "  Mayani Bird Sanctuary ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKeoladeo Ghana National Park in Rajasthan was formerly known as Bharatpur Bird Sanctuary. This National Park is home to diverse bird species including the Siberian Crane. ",
            "keyString": "449153s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the first National Park established in India?",
            "optionA": "  Velvadna National Park ",
            "optionB": "  Periyar National Park ",
            "optionC": "  Bandipur National Park ",
            "optionD": "  Corbett National Park ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCorbett National Park is the first National Park established in India. Corbett National Park, also called Jim Corbett National Park, natural area in southern Uttarakhand state, northern India. It was established as Hailey National Park in 1936 and was first renamed Ramganga in the mid-1950s, before the name was changed to Corbett later that decade in memory of Jim Corbett, a well-known British sportsman and writer.",
            "keyString": "449398s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched? National Park : State",
            "optionA": "  Kanha National Park : Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Sultanpur National Park : Haryana ",
            "optionC": "  Ranthambore National Park : Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Bandipur National Park : Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRanthambore National Park is a vast wildlife reserve near the town of Sawai Madhopur in Rajasthan, northern India.",
            "keyString": "449629s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Namdhapa National Park is in",
            "optionA": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionB": "  Manipur ",
            "optionC": "  Tripura ",
            "optionD": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNamdhapa National Park is situated in Arunachal Pradesh in North East India. It is the third largest National Park of India in terms of area. ",
            "keyString": "449841s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Bandipur National Park?",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "   Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBandipur National Park is situated in Karnataka. It was established in 1974. It was private hunting ground for Maharaja of Mysore.",
            "keyString": "450041s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the first biosphere reserve established in India?",
            "optionA": "  Nilgiri ",
            "optionB": "  Nanda Devi ",
            "optionC": "  Hazaribagh ",
            "optionD": "  Kanha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNilgiri is one of the International Biosphere Reserve in India. In the year 1987, it became the first biosphere reserve of India. Lying at juncture of 3 states it has endemic flora & fauna of Western Ghats. ",
            "keyString": "528495s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the first Bio-reserve established in India?",
            "optionA": "  Nokrek ",
            "optionB": "  Kanha ",
            "optionC": "  Nilgiris ",
            "optionD": "  Periyal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt became Biosphere reserve in 1986. It is the southern part of Western Ghats. It is at the tri-junction of Karnataka, Kerala & Tamil Nadu.",
            "keyString": "528988s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is also known as Top Slip?",
            "optionA": "  Simlipal National Park ",
            "optionB": "  Periyar Wildlife Sanctuary ",
            "optionC": "  Manjira Wildlife Sanctuary ",
            "optionD": "  Indira Gandhi Wildlife Sanctuary and National Park ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndira Gandhi Wildlife Sanctuary and National Park is also known as Top Slip. It is located in Annamalai hills of Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "529179s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mudumalai Wild life Sanctuary is located in the state of",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Paradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMudurnalai National Park & Wild life Sanctuary is located in Nilgiri District in Tamil Nadu. It shares boundaries with neighboring state of Kerala & Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "529354s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The \"Valley of Flowers\" is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "optionB": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Valley of Flowers' is a National Park instate of Uttarakhand in Western Himalayas. eg. Asiatic black bear, snow leopard etc. are found. Valley of Flowers along with Nanda Devi National Park makes up Nanda Devi Biosphere Reserve. ",
            "keyString": "529548s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kaziranga National Park is famous for which of the following",
            "optionA": "  Rhinos ",
            "optionB": "  Tiger ",
            "optionC": "  Deer ",
            "optionD": "  Elephant ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKaziranga National Park has about 2/3rd of world's great one horned rhinoceroses. It is situated in Assam as a renowned \"World Heritage Site\". ",
            "keyString": "600871s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is considered as the \"forest of world heritage\"?",
            "optionA": "  Nandankanan in Orissa ",
            "optionB": "  Kaziranga in Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Sundarban in West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Indian botanic garden, Shibpur in West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSundarbans lie in Ganga Brahmaputra delta. They are one of the largest mangrove forests in the world. It was designated as World Heritage Site by UNESCO in 1987. ",
            "keyString": "601126s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A person wants to visit the national parks in Ranthambhor, Gir and Bandipur located in three different states of India. To which one of the following states does he need not go in this connection?",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe need not go Kerala in this connection. One of the largest national parks in Northern India, Ranthambore is famous for its tigers and it is the only place in India where these royal predators can be spotted in the jungle, even during the day. Bandipur National Park is situated in the Chamarajanagar district in Karnataka, Southern part of India. It is one of the oldest wildlife sanctuaries in India established in 1931 and a protected reserve for tigers. The Gir Forest National Park is located in the Indian state of Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "601358s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is famous \"GIR\" forest located?",
            "optionA": "  Mysore ",
            "optionB": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Gir forests are natural habitat of Asiatic lions. Its known as Gir Forest National Park & Wildlife Santuary. It is located in Kathiawar region of Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "601559s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Namdapha is a national park in",
            "optionA": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionB": "  Manipur ",
            "optionC": "  Tripura ",
            "optionD": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNamdapha National Park is third largest in India. It is also a biodiversity hot spot in Eastern Himalayas. It is located in Arunachal Pradesh. It has tropical rain forests. It has Tiger reserve. ",
            "keyString": "601756s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sariska and Ranthambore are the reserves for which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Lion ",
            "optionB": "  Deer ",
            "optionC": "  Tiger ",
            "optionD": "  Bear ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSariska Tiger Reserve is in Alwar & Ranthambore, Tiger Reserve is in Sawai Madhopur district of Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "696935s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The problem of arsenic in India is due to",
            "optionA": "  Overexploitation of surface water inaffected areas ",
            "optionB": "  Overexploitation of arsenopyrite in land ",
            "optionC": "  Overexploitation of coal in Bihar and Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Overexploitation of ground water in affected areas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBeing heavy the concentration of arsenic in the lower levels of underground water keeps on increasing, As the water table shrinks the concentration of Arsenic increases automatically which is hazardous to health, e.g. in Ganga Brahmaputra basin. ",
            "keyString": "697589s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is known as \"Bio-Diversity\" hotspot of India\"?",
            "optionA": "  Western Ghats ",
            "optionB": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionC": "  Western Himalayas ",
            "optionD": "  Eastern Himalayas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWestern Ghats have around 1800 endemic species. Most of them Me endangered due to human activities in the region. Hence, it is made the bio-diversity hotspot so as to save the receding species of this region. ",
            "keyString": "697960s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Geothermal energy may serve as an important source of energy in",
            "optionA": "  The Konkan Coast ",
            "optionB": "  Ladakh District ",
            "optionC": "  Aravalli Hills ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada Valley ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGeothermal energy is thermal energy generated and stored in the Earth. Geothermal energy may serve as an important source of energy in Ladakh District. ",
            "keyString": "698158s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India the most important source of energy is",
            "optionA": "  Petroleum ",
            "optionB": "  Coal ",
            "optionC": "  Nuclear ",
            "optionD": "  Hydro-electricity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India the most important source of energy is Coal. Coal is the main source of energy in India and it accounts for about 67% of country's commercial requirements.",
            "keyString": "698340s3m35h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}